<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Travis Ci on Yongfu&#39;s Blog</title><link>https://yongfu.name/tags/travis-ci/</link><description>Recent content in Travis Ci on Yongfu&#39;s Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yongfu.name/tags/travis-ci/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What if I Have No Server?</title><link>https://yongfu.name/2020/05/26/what-if-i-have-no-server/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yongfu.name/2020/05/26/what-if-i-have-no-server/</guid><description>In my previous post, I describe how I created a web app that can search and locate patterns in interlinear glosses written in Word documents (docx) to facilitate the workflow of documenting language. I tried to make the (backend) app extremely easy to install, but still, most of my classmates didn&amp;rsquo;t even try to install it. It is just to frightening for people without any programming experience to install python on their own.</description></item><item><title>Visualizing Language Loss in Taiwan</title><link>https://yongfu.name/2019/02/17/visualize-language-loss/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yongfu.name/2019/02/17/visualize-language-loss/</guid><description>Taiwan Language Survey is a small project I worked on during May to June in 2018. The idea was to create a survey that continuously collects data and a web page that visualizes the collected data. The web page is updated weekly using Travis-CI.
The main purpose of this survey is to raise public awareness of language loss in Taiwan. Hence, the survey is designed to collect data that can provide valuable information about language loss, for example, some questions were asked to gain insight about the change of linguistic competence acoss generations in a family (i.</description></item><item><title>Using Travis-CI to Create R-bloggers for Taiwan</title><link>https://yongfu.name/2019/01/30/recreate-rbloggers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yongfu.name/2019/01/30/recreate-rbloggers/</guid><description>R-bloggers.com is a great platform for R users, but I sometimes feel awkward to publish posts on R-bloggers when I have things to share that are only relevant to users in Taiwan1. Inspired by R-bloggers, I thought maybe I could use Travis-CI and GitHub to create a blog that automatically updates its posts by retrieving them from submitted RSS feeds, just like R-bloggers.
R-bloggers for Taiwan The name of the blog I created is &amp;ldquo;R部落客&amp;rdquo;, which is R-bloggers literally in traditional Chinese.</description></item></channel></rss>